What is it about flying cars?
ما الفريد بخصوص السيارات الطائرة؟
We've wanted to do this for about a hundred years.
أردنا القيام بذلك لأكثر من مئة عام.
And there are historic attempts
وهناك محاولات تاريخية
that have had some level of technical success.
والتي كللت بدرجة من النجاح التقني.
But we haven't yet gotten to the point
لكننا لم نصل بعد إلى النقطة
where on your way here this morning
حيث وفي طريقك إلى هنا هذا الصباح
you see something that really, truly seamlessly integrates
ترى شيئا يدمج حقا وبسلاسة
the two-dimensional world that we're comfortable in
العالم الثنائي الأبعاد الذي نحن مرتاحون فيه
with the three-dimensional sky above us --
مع السماء الثلاثية الأبعاد فوقنا --
that, I don't know about you, but I really enjoy spending time in.
والتي، لست أدري عنكم، لكنني أستمتع حقا بقضاء الوقت فيها.
We looked at the historical attempts that had been out there
نظرنا إلى المحاولات التاريخية التي سبقت
and realized that, despite the fact
وأدركنا أنه، على الرغم من حقيقة
that we have a lot of modern innovations
أنه لدينا الكثير من الاختراعات الحديثة
to draw on today
للاعتماد عليها اليوم
that weren't available previously --
والتي لم تكن متوفرة من قبل --
we have modern composite materials,
لدينا المواد المركبة الحديثة،
we have aircraft engines that get good fuel economy
لدينا محركات طائرات لديها تدبير جيد للوقود
and have better power-to-rate ratios than have ever been available,
ولديها نسبة قوة-إلى-معدل أفضل من التي كانت متوفرة،
we have glass cockpit avionics
لدينا إلكترونيات طيران زجاجية في مقصورة الطيران
that bring the information you need to fly
والتي تجلب المعلومات التي تحتاجها للطيران
directly to you in the cockpit --
مباشرة لك في مقصورة الطيران --
but without fundamentally addressing the problem from a different perspective,
لكن من دون التعاطي مع المشكلة الأساسية بمقاربة مختلفة،
we realized that we were going to be getting
أدركنا أننا سنحصل على
the same result that people had been getting
نفس النتائج التي حصل عليها الناس
for the last hundred years,
في المئة سنة الأخيرة،
which isn't where we want to be right now.
والتي ليست بالمكان الذي نريد أن نكون فيه حاليا.
So instead of trying to make a car that can fly,
وبالتالي بدل محاولة صناعة سيارة يمكنها الطيران،
we decided to try to make a plane that could drive.
قررنا محاولة صناعة سيارة يمكنك سياقتها.
And the result is the Terrafugia Transition.
والنتيجة هي مرحلة تحول التيرافوغيا .
It's a two-seat, single-engine airplane
إنها سيارة ذات محرك واحد ومقعدين
that works just like any other small airplane.
تعمل تماما مثل أي طائرة صغيرة أخرى.
You take off and land at a local airport.
تقلع وتهبط في مطار محلي.
Then once you're on the ground,
ثم بمجرد أن تصل إلى الأرض،
you fold up the wings, drive it home,
تجمع الجناحين، وتسوقها إلى البيت،
park it in your garage.
وتركنها في مرأبك.
And it works.
وقد نجح الأمر
After two years of an innovative design and construction process,
بعد سنتين من التصميم الإبداعي وعملية البناء،
the proof of concept made its public debut
الدليل على الفكرة ظهر علنيا لأول مرة
in 2008.
عام 2008.
Now like with anything
الآن وكأي أمر
that's really different from the status quo,
مختلف حقا عن الوضع الراهن،
it didn't always go so well testing that aircraft.
لم يكن من اليسير دائما تجربة تلك الطائرة.
And we discovered that it's a very good thing
واكتشفنا أنه أمر جيد
that, when you go home with something that's been broken,
أنه، حين تعود إلى البيت بشيء مكسور،
you've actually learned a lot more
تكون بالفعل قد تعلمت أكثر بكثير
than when you managed to tick off all of your test objectives
من حين تنجح في تحقيق أهداف اختبارك
the first time through.
في أول مرة.
Still, we very much wanted to see
مع ذلك، أردنا جميعا بشدة أن نرى
the aircraft that we'd all helped build
الطائرة التي ساعدنا في بنائها
in the air, off the ground,
في السماء، فوق الأرض،
like it was supposed to be.
كما يفترض بها أن تكون.
And on our third high-speed testing deployment
وفي اختبارنا الثالث للانتشار السريع
on a bitter cold morning in upstate New York,
في صباح قارس البرد في ضواحي نيويورك،
we got to do that for the first time.
أمكننا القيام بذلك للمرة الأولى.
The picture behind me was snapped by the copilot in our chase aircraft
الصورة خلفي تم التقاطها من طرف مساعد الطيار في طائرتنا المطاردة
just moments after the wheels got off the ground for the first time.
بعد لحظات من ابتعاد العجلات عن الأرض لأول مرة.
And we were all very flattered to see that image
وقد كنا جميعا سعداء برؤية تلك الصورة
become a symbol of accomplishing something
تصبح رمزا لتحقيق شيء
that people had thought was impossible
اعتقد الناس أنه مستحيل
really the world over.
في العالم كله.
The flight testing that followed that
طيران الاختبار الذي تلاه
was as basic and low-risk as we could make it,
كان أساسيا وبأقل مجازفة أمكننا القيام بها،
but it still accomplished what we needed to
لكنه مع ذلك حقق ما احتجناه
to take the program to the next step
لأخذ البرنامج إلى الخطوة التالية
and to gain the credibility that we needed
وحيازة المصداقية التي احتجنا لها
within our eventual market, the general aviation community,
داخل سوقنا المرغوب فيه، مجتمع الطيران العام،
and with the regulators
ومع المشرعين
that govern the use of design of aircraft, particularly in the States.
الذين يحكمون في استخدام تصميم الطائرات، بالخصوص في الولايات المتحدة.
The FAA, about a year ago,
إدارة الطيران الفيدرالية، وقبل حوالي السنة،
gave us an exemption for the Transition
أعطونا استثناء للمتحولة
to allow us to have an additional 110 lbs.
بالسماح لنا بـ 110 رطلا إضافيا.
within the light sport aircraft category.
في إطار تصنيف الطائرات الخفيفة الرياضية.
Now that doesn't sound like a lot, but it's very important,
الآن لا يبدو ذلك كشيء كثير، لكنه في غاية الأهمية،
because being able to deliver the Transition as a light sport aircraft
لأن أن نكون قادرين على تقديم المتحولة كطائرة رياضية خفيفة
makes it simpler for us to certify it,
يجعل المصادقة عليها أسهل علينا،
but it also makes it much easier
لكنه كذلك يجعلها أكثر سهولة
for you to learn how to fly it.
لك لتعلم كيفية التحليق بها.
A sport pilot can be certificated
طيار رياضي يمكنه الحصول على الرخصة
in as little as 20 hours of flight time.
في مدة وجيزة قدرها 20 ساعة من الطيران.
And at 110 lbs.,
وفي 110 رطل،
that's very important for solving the other side of the equation --
ذلك في غاية الأهمية لحل الشق الثاني من المعادلة --
driving.
السياقة.
It turns out that driving,
وقد اتضح أن السياقة،
with its associated design implementation and regulatory hurdles,
بالعقبات التصميمية والتشريعية المرتبطة بها،
is actually a harder problem to solve than flying.
هي بالفعل مشكلة حلها أصعب من الطيران.
For those of us that spend most of our lives on the ground,
بالنسبة لمعظمنا الذين قضوا جل حياتهم على الأرض،
this may be counter-intuitive,
قد يكون هذا غير بديهي،
but driving has potholes, cobblestones,
لكن السياقة لديها حصى وحفر
pedestrians, other drivers
ومشاة والسائقون الآخرون
and a rather long and detailed list
ولائحة طويلة ومفصلة بالأحرى
of federal motor vehicle safety standards to contend with.
للمعايير الفيدرالية لسلامة السيارات للتعامل معها.
Fortunately, necessity remains the mother of invention,
من حسن الحظ، الحاجة تبقى أم الاختراع،
and a lot of the design work
والكثير من أعمال التصميم
that we're the most proud of with the aircraft
التي نحن فخورون بها أكثر مع هذه الطائرة
came out of solving the unique problems
أتت من حل مشاكل فريدة
of operating it on the ground --
لتشغيلها على الأرض --
everything from a continuously-variable transmission
كل شيء من الانتقال المتغير باستمرار
and liquid-based cooling system
ونظام التبريد المعتمد على السوائل
that allows us to use an aircraft engine
الذي يسمح لنا باستخدام محرك طائرة
in stop-and-go traffic,
في حركة سير كلها توقف وانتقال،
to a custom-designed gearbox
بعلبة سرعة بتصميم مخصص
that powers either the propeller when you're flying or the wheels on the ground,
والتي تشغل إما المروحة حين تكون محلقا والعجلات حين تكون على الأرض،
to the automated wing-folding mechanism that we'll see in a moment,
مرورا بميكانيزم طي الجناح الأوتوماتيكي والذي سوف نراه في لحظات،
to crash safety features.
وصولا إلى خصائص سلامة التحطم.
We have a carbon fiber safety cage
لدينا قفص سلامة من ألياف الكربون
that protects the occupants
الذي يحمي الركاب
for less than 10 percent of the weight of a traditional steel chassis in a car.
بأقل ب10 في المئة من الوزن الاعتيادي لهيكل الكرسي الصلب في سيارة.
Now this also, as good as it is, wasn't quite enough.
هذا أيضا، بقدر ما هو جيد، لم يكن كافيا تماما.
The regulations for vehicles on the road
قوانين السيارات في الطريق
weren't written with an airplane in mind.
لم تكن مكتوبة باخذ طائرة في الاعتبار.
So we did need a little bit of support
لذلك احتجنا إلى القليل من الدعم
from the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration.
من الإدارة الوطنية لسلامة المرور على الطرق السريعة.
Now you may have seen in the news recently,
قد تكونوا رأيتم في الأخبار مؤخرا،
they came through with us at the end of last month
استجابوا لنا في نهاية الشهر الماضي
with a few special exemptions
باعفاءات خاصة
that will allow the Transition to be sold
ستسمح للمتحولة بأن تباع
in the same category as SUVs and light trucks.
في نفس تصنيف سيارات الدفع الرباعي والشاحنات الخفيفة.
As a multi-purpose passenger vehicle,
كسيارات ركاب متعددة الوظائف،
it is now officially "designed for occasional off-road use."
إنها الآن رسميا "مصممة للاستعمال الموسمي خارج الطريق."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now let's see it in action.
الآن دعونا نراه تشتغل.
You can see there the wings folded up just along the side of the plane.
يمكنكم أن تروا الجناحين مطويين هناك على جانبي الطائرة.
You're not powering the propeller, you're powering the wheels.
لا نقوم بتزويد المروحة بالطاقة، بل العجلات.
And it is under seven feet tall,
وهي بعلو أقل من سبعة أقدام،
so it will fit in a standard construction garage.
وبالتالي ستلائم مرآب قياسي البناء.
And that's the automated wing-folding mechanism.
وتلك هي آلية طي الجناح الأوتوماتيكية.
That's real time.
هذا بالوقت الحقيقي.
You just push a few buttons in the cockpit, and the wings come out.
تقوم فقط بالضغط على بضعة أزرار في مقصورة الطيار، فيخرج الجناحان.
Once they're fully deployed,
بمجرد أن ينشرا كليا،
there's a mechanical lock that goes into place,
هناك قفل ميكانيكي يتموضع في المكان،
again, from inside the cockpit.
مجددا، من داخل مقصورة الطيار.
And they're now fully capable of handling
وهي الآن قادرة كليا على التعامل مع
any of the loads you would see in flight --
أي من الأحمال التي قد ترون في الرحلة --
just like putting down your convertible top.
تماما مثل إنزال سقف سيارة مكشوفة.
And you're all thinking what your neighbors would think of seeing that.
وجميعكم يفكر فيم قد يظنه جيرانكم حين يرون ذلك.
(Video) Test Pilot: Until the vehicle flies,
(فيديو) الطيار الاختباري: حتى تطير المركبة،
75 percent of your risk is that first flight.
75 في المئة من الخطر هي الرحلة الأولى.
Radio: It actually flew. Yes.
راديو: لقد طارت بالفعل. نعم.
Radio 2: That was gorgeous.
راديو 2: ذلك كان رائعا.
Radio: What did you think of that?
راديو: ما الذي اعتقدته من ذلك؟
That was beautiful from up here, I tell you.
ذاك كان رائعا من الأعلى هنا، أؤكد لك.
AMD: See, we're all exceedingly excited about that little bunny hop.
أ.م.د: ترون أننا جميعا متحمسون لقفزة الأرنب الصغيرة تلك.
And our test pilot gave us
وطيارنا الاختباري أعطانا
the best feedback you can get from a test pilot after a first flight,
أحسن رد فعل يمكن أن تحص عليه من طيار اختباري بعد الطيران الأول،
which was that it was "remarkably unremarkable."
وهو أنه كان "غير ملحوظ بشكل ملحوظ."
He would go onto tell us
وسيواصل ويخبرنا
that the Transition had been the easiest airplane to land
أن المتحولة هي لحد الآن أسهل طائرة للهبوط بها
that he'd flown in his entire 30-year career as a test pilot.
من الطائرات التي حلق بها طوال 30 سنة من مسيرته المهنية كطيار اختبار.
So despite making something
إذن رغم صناعة شيء
that is seemingly revolutionary,
يبدو ثوريا،
we really focused on doing
ركزنا فعلا على القيام
as little new as possible.
بأقل ما يمكن من الجديد.
We leverage a lot of technology from the state-of-the-art in general aviation
استخدمنا الكثير من آخر مستحدثات تكنولوجيا الطيران العام
and from automotive racing.
ومن سباق السيارات.
When we do have to do something truly out-of-the-box,
حين يتوجب علينا أن نقوم بشيء إستثنائي حقا ،
we use an incremental design, build, test, redesign cycle
نستخدم دورة إعادة تصميم بتصميم وبناء وتجريب دائري
that lets us reduce risk in baby steps.
الذي تسمح لنا بتخفيض الخطر بخطوات بطيئة.
Now since we started Terrafugia about 6 years ago,
الآن منذ أن بدأنا تيرافويغيا قبل حوالي 6 سنوات،
we've had a lot of those baby steps.
عرفنا الكثير من هذه الخطوات البطيئة.
We've gone from being three of us
انتقلنا من مجرد ثلاثتنا
working in the basement at MIT while we were still in graduate school
نعمل في قبو في MIT حين كنا لا نزال في الدراسات العليا
to about two-dozen of us
إلى حوالي مجموعتين منا
working in an initial production facility outside of Boston.
نعمل في مرفق إنتاج أولي خارج بوسطن.
We've had to overcome challenges
كان علينا تجاوز تحديات
like keeping the weight below the light sport limit that I talked about,
مثل الحفاظ على الوزن دون تصنيف الرياضية الخفيفة الذي تحدثت عنه،
figuring out how to politely respond
معرفة كيفية الرد
when a regulator tells you,
حين يخبرك مشرع،
"But that won't fit through a toll booth with the wings extended --
"لكن ذلك لن يتلاءم مع كشك تحصيل الرسوم على الطريق إن كان الجناحان ممددان --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
to all of the other associated durability and engineering issues
مرورا بكل المشاكل الهندسية تلك المرتبطة بالمتانة
that we talked about on the ground.
التي تحدثت عنها على الأرض.
Still, if everything goes to our satisfaction
مع ذلك، إن تم كل شيء حسب ما نرتضيه
with the testing and construction
في اختبار وبناء
of the two production prototypes
نموذجي الإنتاج
that we're working on right now,
التي نعمل عليهما الآن،
those first deliveries
تلك الشحنات الأولى
to the, about a hundred, people who have reserved an airplane at this point
لحوالي مئة شخص من الذين حجزوا هذه الطائرة لحد الآن
should begin at the end of next year.
ستبدأ في نهاية السنة القادمة.
The Transition will cost in line with other small airplanes.
كلفة المتحولة ستكون في نفس نطاق الطائرات الصغيرة الأخرى.
And I'm certainly not out to replace your Chevy,
وأنا بكل تأكيد لست أسعى لتعويض تشيفي،
but I do think that the Transition should be your next airplane.
لكنني أعتقد ان المتحولة يجب أن تكون طائرتكم التالية.
Here's why.
ها هو السبب.
While nearly all of the commercial air travel in the world
في حين كل الرحلات التجارية الجوية في العالم تقريبا
goes through a relatively small number of large hub airports,
تتم عن طريق عدد صغير نسبيا من محاور المطارات الكبرى،
there is a huge underutilized resource out there.
هناك الكثير من الموارد غير المستغلة في الخارج.
There are thousands of local airstrips
هناك الآلاف من مهابط الطائرات المحلية
that don't see nearly as many aircraft operations a day as they could.
التي لا ترى حتى مقدار عمليات الطائرات يوميا التي يمكنها.
On average, there's one within 20 to 30 miles
في المتوسط، هناك واحد ضمن 20 إلى 30 ميلا
of wherever you are in the United States.
في أي مكان تكون فيه في الولايات المتحدة.
The Transition gives you
المتحولة تعطيك
a safer, more convenient and more fun way
طريقة أكثر سلامة وراحة ومتعة
of using this resource.
لاستخدام هذه الموارد.
For those of you who aren't yet pilots,
لمن منكم ليس ربانا بعد،
there's four main reasons why those of us who are
هناك أربعة أسباب رئيسية تدفع من هم كذلك منا
don't fly as much as we'd like to:
إلى عدم الطيران بقدر ما نريد:
the weather, primarily,
الطقس، أساسا،
cost, long door-to-door travel time
التكلفة، طول مسافة السفر من الباب إلى الباب
and mobility at your destination.
والتنقل في وجهة الوصول.
Now, bad weather comes in,
الآن، حين يحل الطقس السيء،
just land, fold up the wings, drive home.
فقط اهبط، قم بطي الجناحين، وقم بالقيادة إلى البيت.
Doesn't matter if it rains a little, you have a windshield wiper.
لا يهم إن سقط قليل من المطر، لديك مساحة للزجاج الأمامي.
Instead of paying to keep your airplane in a hanger,
بدل دفع النقود للإبقاء على طائرتك في حظيرة الطائرات،
park it in your garage.
اركنها في مرأبك.
And the unleaded automotive fuel that we use
ووقود السيارات الخالي من الرصاص الذي نستخدمه
is both cheaper and better for the environment
هو في نفس الوقت أرخص وأفضل للبيئة
than traditional avgas.
من وقود الطائرات.
Door-to-door travel time is reduced,
مدة السفر من الباب إلى الباب تقلصت،
because now, instead of lugging bags, finding a parking space,
لأنه الآن، بدل سحب الحقائب، إيجاد مكان للركن،
taking off your shoes or pulling your airplane out of the hanger,
إزالة حذائك أو إخراج طائرتك من الحظيرة،
you're now just spending that time getting to where you want to go.
تستغرق ذلك الوقت الآن فقط للوصول إلى حيث تريد الذهاب.
And mobility to your destination is clearly solved.
والتنقل إلى الوجهة تم بوضوح حلها.
Just fold up the wings and keep going.
فقط اطو الجناحين واستمر في التحرك.
The Transition simultaneously expands our horizons
المتحولة توسع كذلك آفاقنا
while making the world a smaller, more accessible place.
مع جعل العالم أصغر وأسهل المنال.
It also continues to be a fabulous adventure.
تستمر كذلك في كونها مغامرة رائعة.
I hope you'll each take a moment
آمل أن يستغرق كل منكم لحظة
to think about how you could use something like this
للتفكير في كيفية استخدام شيء كهذا
to give yourself more access to your own world,
لإعطاء أنفسكم وصولا أكثر لعالمكم الخاص،
and to make your own travel more convenient and more fun.
وجعل سفركم أكثر ملائمة ومتعة.
Thank you for giving me the opportunity to share it with you.
شكرا لكم على إعطائي الفرصة لمشاركة هذا معكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)